Henry Trantham papers, Inclusive: 1894-1962, undated, Bulk:1921-1950, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Henry Trantham papers
Inclusive: 1894-1962, undated, Bulk:1921-1950, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
207
Trantham, Henry, 1882 - 1962
8 document boxes and 2 oversized folders.
The Henry Trantham papers consist of documents generated and collected by Henry Trantham. The papers contain correspondence, administrative and academic materials, and other loose materials related to Baylor University and the Greek and Classics Departments, the Southwest Athletic Conference, and the Rhodes Scholarship program.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Henry Trantham was born on 1882 March 10 in Camden, South Carolina. He received a Bachelor of Arts and Master of Arts Degree from Wake Forrest College in 1900 and 1901, and attended the University of Oxford through the Rhodes Scholarship from 1905 to 1908. Trantham taught at the Oak Ridge Institute in Oak Ridge, North Carolina, from 1902 to 1905, and served as the principal at the Newnan High School in Newnan, Georgia, from 1908 to 1910. He was a professor of Greek and Roman History, Twentieth Century History, and Greek language at Baylor University from 1910 to 1958, serving as the Greek Department head from 1910 to 1950, and Classics Department chairman from 1950 to 1958. Trantham retired in 1958 and died on 1962 February 19.
Henry Trantham served on multiple committees and boards. He was the Baylor University faculty representative to the Southwest Athletic Conference from 1916 to 1923, and from 1925 to 1941. Trantham was the president of the Southwest Athletic Conference from 1918 to 1919, and from 1938 to 1941, and in that position he assisted in the establishment of the Cotton Bowl Association. He was the secretary for the Rhodes Scholarship Selection committee from 1919 to 1939. Trantham was a member of the Board of Commissioners, City of Waco, Texas, from 1931 to 1933. He was a member of the Philosophical Society of Texas, the Texas Classical Association, the Philosopher’s Club of Waco, Texas, and Phi Beta Kappa. At Baylor University, Trantham was the editor of “The Diamond Jubilee, 1845-1920”.
Scope and Content
The Henry Trantham papers contain six series, organized mostly chronologicaly. Most of the materials are handwritten in pencil. It contains correspondence related to the Southwest Athletic Conference from 1921 to 1941; correspondence related to Baylor University administration, the Classics Department and the Diamond Jubilee; correspondence related to the Rhodes Scholarship, in the context of Rhodes Scholarship alumni and the selection process for new Rhodes Scholars; and personal correspondence. The correspondence was generated by Henry Trantham and by others, and includes drafts of letters frequently written on the back of lesson plans and student exams. It also contains Baylor University grade books for Greek and History classes from 1910 to 1958, primarily in bound book form. It contains lesson plans for Greek language classes and History classes. There are newsletters and materials related to the Rhodes Scholarship, from 1920 to 1958. Meeting minutes, team rosters, newspaper clippings and other materials related to the Southwest Athletic Conference are also included. There are a few receipts and other personal materials.
The Henry Trantham papers, particularly the correspondence series, provides useful information about the Southwest Athletic Conference, particularly information about team rosters, constitutional discussions and eligibility issues. The correspondence and Baylor Academic Materials series provide useful Greek language lesson plans, which are both in English and Greek.
Arrangement
The Henry Trantham papers were not organized prior to processing, beyond a few folders containing correspondence and lesson plans. The collection had an initial inventory from 1971.
The Henry Trantham papers are organized into six series: I. Correspondence, II. Baylor Grade Books, III. Baylor Academic Materials, IV. Non-Baylor Academic Materials, V. Athletic Materials, VI. Personal Materials.
Access Restrictions
This collection is restricted. Please see an archivist for details.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 207. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
Garrett, James Leo, Jr. The Teacher’s Yolk: Studies in Memory of Henry Trantham. Baylor University Press: Waco, Texas, 1964, pp. 13-16.
International Who’s Who. “The Monthly Suppplement, A Current Adjunct to Who’s Who”. Chicago: A.N. Marquis Co., 1951 July, p. 455.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Rhodes Scholarship.; Southwest Conference (U.S.)
Subjects
Athletics -- Texas.; College sports -- Texas -- History.
Genres
Correspondence.; Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Research notes.
- Correspondence, 1921-1951, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  Series includes correspondence to and from Henry Trantham related to Baylor University, the Rhodes Scholarship and the Southwest Athletic Conference. The material is in fair condition: the sheets are yellowed, and many items are facsimile and carbon copies on thin and worn paper.
  - Baylor University, 1921 April 1-June 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baylor University, 1921 July 11-November 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baylor University, 1921 November 28 - 1922 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Baylor University, 1923 September 4 - 1923 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Baylor University, 1941 May 19 -1941 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baylor University, 1941 May 7 - 1947 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baylor University, 1947 November 25 - 1949 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baylor University, 1949 May 11 - 1951 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baylor University, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rhodes Scholarship, 1921 September 20-October 22 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rhodes Scholarship, 1921 October 24 - December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rhodes Scholarship, 1922 February 21-August 27 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rhodes Scholarship, 1922 September 12 - 1923 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rhodes Scholarship, 1923 June 19 - 1940 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rhodes Scholarship, 1947 February 26 - 1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1922 September 19 - 1922 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1922 September 22 - 1939 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1940 March 27 - 1941 August 17 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1942 May 22 - 1947 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1947 October 11 - 1948 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1948 May 26 - 1949 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1949 December 25 - 1952 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Personal Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Athletics, 1921 March 30 - November 17 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Athletics, 1921 November 21 - 1922 February 17 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Athletics, 1922 February 18 - April 4 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Athletics, 1922 April 18 - May 8 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Athletics, 1922 May 8 - September 22 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Athletics, 1922 September 25 - November 24 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Athletics, 1922 November 24 - December 19 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Athletics, 1923 January 4 - February 17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Athletics, 1923 March 4 - March 28 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Athletics, 1923 April 2 - May 4 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Athletics, 1923 May 8 - December 13 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Athletics, 1939 December 5 - 1941 April 8 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Athletics, 1941 April 9 - May 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Athletics, 1941 May 6 - July 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Athletics, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Baylor Grade Books, 1910-1958, undated; 2
  General condition: Good.
  Series contains 20 grade books and typewritten grade sheets for Greek language and various History classes at Baylor University. The material is in good condition: the books are starting to yellow.
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1910-1912 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1916-1926 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1922-1927 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1944-1946 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Baylor Grade Books, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Baylor Grade Books, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Loose Materials, 1957-1958, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Baylor Academic Materials, 1922-1958, undated; 3
  Series includes lesson plans, midterm and final exams, and class notes related to Greek language, History, Physics and Chemistry classes at Baylor University, along with administrative papers and other materials related to Baylor University. The material is in fair condition: the sheets are yellowed, and many items are facsimile and carbon copies on thin and worn paper.
  - History 301, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - History 301 by Correspondence (1 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - History 301 by Correspondence (2 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - History: General, undated (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Greek 213 (1 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Greek 213 (2 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Greek 213 (3 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Greek 213 (4 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Greek 213 (5 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Greek 213 (6 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Greek 213 (7 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Greek 213 (8 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Greek 213 (9 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Greek 213 (10 of 10), 1955-1956, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Greek 213 (1 of 4), 1957 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Greek 213 (2 of 4), 1957 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Greek 213 (3 of 4), 1957 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Greek 213 (4 of 4), 1957 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Greek 213 (1 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Greek 213 (2 of 6), undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Greek 213 (3 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Greek 213 (4 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Greek 213 (5 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Greek 213 (1 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Greek 213 (2 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Greek 213 (3 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Greek 213 (4 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Greek 213 (5 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Greek 213 (6 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Greek 213 (7 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Greek 213 (8 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Greek 213 (9 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Greek 213 (10 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Greek 213 (11 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Greek 213 (1 of 8), undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Greek 213 (2 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Greek 213 (3 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Greek 213 (4 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Greek 213 (5 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Greek 213 (6 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Greek 213 (7 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Greek 213 (8 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Notes: Greek Language (1 of 9), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Notes: Greek Language (2 of 9), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Notes: Greek Language (3 of 9), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Notes: Greek Language (4 of 9), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Notes: Greek Language (5 of 9), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Notes: Greek Language (6 of 9), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Notes: Greek Language (7 of 9), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Notes: Greek Language (8 of 9), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Notes: Greek Language (9 of 9), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Notes: Greek Language (1 of 7), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Notes: Greek Language (2 of 7), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Notes: Greek Language (3 of 7), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Notes: Greek Language (4 of 7), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Notes: Greek Language (5 of 7), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Notes: Greek Language (6 of 7), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Notes: Greek Language (7 of 7), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Notes: Greek Language (1 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Notes: Greek Language (2 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Notes: Greek Language (3 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Notes: Greek Language (4 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Notes: Greek Language (5 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Notes: Greek Language (6 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Notes: Greek Language (7 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Notes: Greek Language (8 of 8), undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Notes: Greek Language (1 of 4), undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Notes: Greek Language (2 of 4), undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Notes: Greek Language (3 of 4), undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Notes: Greek Language (4 of 4), undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Notes: Herodotus Dictionary, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Translation of John IV, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Paraphrase of John (1 of 12), undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Paraphrase of John (2 of 12), undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Paraphrase of John (3 of 12), undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Paraphrase of John (4 of 12), undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Paraphrase of John (5 of 12), undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Paraphrase of John (6 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Paraphrase of John (7 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Paraphrase of John (8 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Paraphrase of John (9 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Paraphrase of John (10 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Paraphrase of John (11 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Paraphrase of John (12 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Physics 230 Notebook, 1937 (Box 86, Folder 8)
  - Physics 350 Notebook, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Physics 350 Notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Notes: Physics, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Notes: Physics and Chemistry, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Baylor Ceremonies, 1923-1948, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Administration: Faculty, 1947, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Administration: Grades and Credits, 1950, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Administration: Calendars, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Administration: Receipts, 1922-1950 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Baylor Publications, 1922-1939, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - General, 1923, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Non-Baylor Academic Materials, 1908-1960, undated; 4
  Series contains twelve Rhodes Scholarship-related newsletters, two pamphlets related to the Rhodes Scholarship, an Oxford University Address Book, one oversized photograph and three bound essays. The material is in good condition: some of the items are yellowed and show wear on the edges.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - American Rhodes Scholars, Alumni Magazine, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Rhodes Scholar Newsletter, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Rhodes Scholar Newsletter, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Rhodes Scholar Newsletter, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Rhodes Scholar Newsletter, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Rhodes House Christmas Newsletter, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Rhodes House Christmas Newsletter, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Rhodes House Christmas Newsletter, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Rhodes House Christmas Newsletter, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Rhodes House Christmas Newsletter, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Rhodes House Christmas Newsletter, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Rhodes House Christmas Newsletter, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - London House Pamphlet, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Oxford and the Rhodes Scholarship Pamphlet, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Christ Church Oxford Address List, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - The Junior and His Church, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - The Political Satire of the Non-Juror, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - The Morals of the Restoration, 1916 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Rhodes Scholarship Reunion, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - General, 1920-1922, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Rhodes Scholarship Reunion, 1947 (Box [1076] OVZ, Folder 7)
- Athletic Materials, 1921-1952, undated; 5
  Series contains athletic reports, rosters, a Cotton Bowl newspaper clipping scrapbook and other athletic materials. The material is in good condition: some of the items are yellowed.
  - Southwest Athletic Conference Meeting Minutes, 1922-1941 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Southwest Athletic Conference Meeting Minutes, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Southwest Athletic Conference Reports, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Southwest Athletic Conference Constitution and By-Laws, 1929-1930 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Southwest Athletic Conference Constitution and By-Laws, 1932-1933 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Southwest Athletic Conference Constitution and By-Laws, 1935-1938 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Southwest Athletic Conference Constitution and By-Laws, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Cotton Bowl Scrapbook (1 of 6), 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Cotton Bowl Scrapbook (2 of 6), 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Cotton Bowl Scrapbook (3 of 6), 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Cotton Bowl Scrapbook (4 of 6), 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Cotton Bowl Scrapbook (5 of 6), 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Cotton Bowl Scrapbook (6 of 6), 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Baylor Athletic Rosters: Baseball, Fencing, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Baylor Athletic Rosters: Track, Swimming, Tennis, Golf, 1941, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Non-Baylor Athletic Rosters, 1917, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Baylor Meeting Minutes, 1921-1922 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - General: Receipts, 1921-1941 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1940-1952, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - New York World’s Fair Certificate, 1939 (Box [1076] OVZ, Folder 8)
- Personal Materials, 1894-1962, undated; 6
  Series contains musical recital programs, handwritten notes and smoking schedules, receipts and other personal materials. The material is in good condition: some of the items are yellowed.
  - Personal Materials: Recital Materials, 1918-1925 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Personal Materials: Recital Materials, 1926, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Personal Materials: Smoking Schedules, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Personal Materials: Literary Notes (1 of 4), 1958-1962 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Personal Materials: Literary Notes (2 of 4), 1958-1962 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Personal Materials: Literary Notes (3 of 4), 1958-1962 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Personal Materials: Literary Notes (4 of 4), 1958-1962 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Personal Materials: The Monthly Supplement, International Who’s Who, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Personal Materials: Receipts, 1921-1923 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Personal Materials: General, 1894-1961 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Personal Materials: General, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)